A Finding Aid to the Allyn Cox Papers, 1856-1982 AAA.coxally
Archives of American Art
Allyn Cox papers
1856-1982
AAA.coxally
Archives of American Art
10.9 Linear feet
The papers of New York, N.Y., and Washington, D.C. painter and muralist Allyn Cox measure 10.9 linear feet and date from 1856-1982. The collection documents Cox's personal and professional life through biographical material, family and general correspondence, writings and notes, research material, printed material, sketchbooks and loose sketches, and photographs. Photographs are of Cox at work, the Cox family, including Kenyon and Louise Cox, Cox's friends and colleagues, events, and Cox's artwork.
Cox, Allyn
Scope and Contents note
The papers of New York, N.Y., and Washington, D.C. painter and muralist Allyn Cox measure 10.9 linear feet and date from 1856-1982. The collection documents Cox's personal and professional life through biographical material, family and general correspondence, writings and notes, research material, printed material, sketchbooks and loose sketches, and photographs. Photographs are of Cox at work, the Cox family, including Kenyon and Louise Cox, Cox's friends and colleagues, events, and Cox's artwork.
Biographical material includes family birth, death, and marriage certificates, and passports for Cox and his wife Ethel, whom he married in 1927; professional membership cards, awards and certificates; records related to sales of furnishings from the Cox family home in Essex, Massachusetts; and an untranscribed interview of Cox by Tony Janak of NBC TV.
Cox's family correspondence is primarily with his mother, Louise Cox. Also found is correspondence with Cox's sister, Caroline Cox Lansing, and his brother Leonard Cox and Leonard's wife, Sylvia, and letters from Ethel Cox to her mother. Additional correspondence relating to the disposition of Kenyon Cox''s artwork and archives to various institutions, can also be found here.
General correspondence documents Cox's career and professional relationships with artists and architects, including John Barrington Bayley, Fabrizio Cassio, Arthur Conrad, Roscoe DeWitt, Stuart Frost, John Harbeson, Francis Keally, Adrian Lamb, Edward Laning, Charles Downing Lay, Deane Keller, Philip Trammell Shutze, and Cliff Young; art institutions and organizations including the Art Commission of the City of New York, the Art Students League, Dumbarton Oaks, the National Society of Mural Painters, and the Smithsonian Institution; federal, state and local government agencies including the American Battle Monuments Commission, the Architect of the Capitol, and the General Grant National Memorial; members of Congress including founder of the United States Capitol Historical Society, Representative Fred Schwengel; and private social clubs in which Cox was active, including the Century Association, the Cosmopolitan Club and the Cosmos Club. Correspondence documents Cox's most well known commissions including work for the George Washington Masonic National Memorial and the United States Capitol, as well as work for many private clients including banks and residences.
Also found are typescripts, manuscripts and notes for Cox's lectures, as well as Ethel Cox's diary from 1923-1936 and her diary excerpt from 1955. Ten folders of research files, consisting primarily of clippings, comprise Cox's source material. Additional printed material provides scattered documentation of Cox's career through announcements and catalogs, and magazine and newspaper articles written by him or about his work. Also found is one folder of clippings about Kenyon Cox.
Four sketchbooks and circa twenty-two loose animal, figure, architectural and landscape sketches comprise Cox's artwork, in addition to two 1943 sketches Cox entered into a War Department mural competition. Also found is an 1873 sketchbook of Kenyon Cox, with sketches of people and scenes in Ohio.
Photographs are of Cox from childhood to the 1980s; his family, including parents, siblings, and grandparents; friends including Philip Trammell Shutze and Warner Bishop; family residences; artist models; events; and artwork, including many of Cox's commissions. In addition to photographic prints, slides, and negatives, the series includes vintage formats such as an ambrotype, 8 tintypes, 2 cyanotypes, and a platinum print. Of particular note are circa 16 photos of Kenyon Cox, one taken by Pirie MacDonald and three of him teaching a class at the Art Students League, and a series of circa 1906 photos taken in a garden, of Louise and Kenyon Cox with their children and others. Also found are 10 glass plate negatives of artwork by Cox.
Related Archival Materials note
Also found in the Archives of American Art are the Allyn Cox papers relating to U.S. Capitol murals, 1970-1974, donated by the Committee on House Administration, via Cindy Szady in 1981. Papers include a resume; a cost estimate by Cox for designing and executing mural decorations in the U.S. Capitol, 1970; a letter, 1974, from the Office of the Architect of the Capitol to the Capitol Historical Society enclosing photocopies of printed material pertinent to the unveiling and dedication of the Capitol rotunda frieze in 1954; miscellaneous printed material, 1971-1974; and 15 photographs of the murals in the Capitol.
Biographical/Historical note
New York, N.Y. and Washington, D.C. painter and muralist, Allyn Cox (1896-1982), was born in New York City to artists Kenyon and Louise Cox. Cox first trained as his father’s assistant, serving as an apprentice to Kenyon Cox during the painting of the murals at the Wisconsin State Capitol, circa 1912. He attended the National Academy of Design from 1910-1915, and the Art Student’s League with George Bridgman in 1915. In 1916 he was awarded the Prix de Rome and subsequently studied at the American Academy in Rome for 2 years before returning to New York City to begin a career in mural painting.
Cox completed numerous murals and decorative paintings for private residences, businesses, churches, and public buildings. Some of his most famous commissions included murals for the Royal Arch Room and Memorial Hall of the George Washington Masonic National Memorial in Alexandria, Virginia; the Law School at the University of Virginia, Charlottesville; and the William A. Clark Memorial Library at the University of California, Los Angeles; panels for the National City Bank, the Continental Bank, and the Guaranty Trust Company in New York; and glass mosaics and inlaid stone maps for the United States Military Cemetery in Hamm, Luxembourg.
Cox is best known for his work in the United States Capitol, beginning in 1952 when he undertook a congressional commission to restore and complete the murals in in the Capitol rotunda begun by Constantino Brumidi and Filipo Costaggini in 1878. Over the course of the next two decades Cox, now residing in Washington, D.C., restored the Frieze of American History and the Apotheosis of Washington in the Rotunda, and designed murals for three first-floor corridors in the Capitol's House wing, now known as the Cox Corridors. Assisted by Cliff Young, Cox completed painting for two of these corridors before his death. In 1958 Cox also painted a portrait of Henry Clay for the Senate Reception Room and in 1975 completed a mural depicting the 1969 moon landing in the Brumidi Corridor.
Cox taught at the Art Students League in 1940 and 1941, and was active in professional organizations throughout his career. He served as President of the American Artists Professional League and the National Society of Mural Painters, and Vice President of both the Fine Arts Federation and the New York Architectural League. He was a member of the board of the New York Municipal Art Society and served on the the New York City Art Commission.
Cox retired in March 1982 at the age of 86 and died the following September.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The bulk of the Allyn Cox papers was donated in 1977 and 1983 by the Estate of Allyn Cox, Stephen M. Pulsifer, Exectuor, including material that had been loaned for microfiliming in 1969. Two mural sketches were donated by the Essex County Greenbelt Association in 1984.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and are closed to researchers,
Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 7 series. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and are closed to researchers.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1916-1982 (0.33 linear feet; Boxes 1, 12)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1878-1982 (6.74 linear feet; Boxes 1-7, 12)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, 1919-1982 (0.58 linear feet; Boxes 7-8)
Series 4: Research Files, circa 1950s-circa 1970s (0.25 linear feet; Box 8)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1920s-1982 (0.5 linear feet; Boxes 8-9)
Series 6: Sketchbooks and Sketches, 1873-circa 1978 (0.25 linear feet; Box 9, OVs 13-14)
Series 7: Photographs, 1856-circa 1980 (2.25 linear feet; Boxes 9-12, OV 13)
American Battle Monuments Commission.; Art Commission of the City of New York.; Art Students League (New York, N.Y.).; Bayley, John Barrington, 1914-1981; Bishop, Warner; Cassio, Fabrizio; Century Association (New York, N.Y.).; Conrad, Arthur; Cosmos Club. (Washington, D.C.); Cox, Ethel; Cox, Kenyon, 1856-1919; Cox, Louise Howland King, 1865-1945; DeWitt, Roscoe, 1894-1975; Dumbarton Oaks.; Frost, Stuart; George Washington Masonic National Memorial. (Alexandria, Va.); Harbeson, John F., 1888-1986, (John Frederick); Keally, Francis, 1889-1978; Keller, Deane, 1901-1992; Lamb, Adrian; Laning, Edward, 1906-; Lay, Charles Downing, 1877-1956; MacDonald, Pirie, 1867-1942; National Society of Mural Painters (New York, N.Y.); Park Club of Kalamazoo.; Schwengel, Fred, 1907-1993; Shutze, Philip Trammell; Smithsonian Institution.; United States Capitol Historical Society.; Young, Clifford, 1905-; Diaries; General Grant National Memorial (New York, N.Y.); Interviews; Muralists--New York (State)--New York; Muralists--Washington (D.C.); Painters--New York (State)--New York; Painters--Washington (D.C.); Photographs; Sketchbooks; Sketches
- Biographical Material, 1916-1982; Series 1; 0.33 Linear feet Boxes 1, 12
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material includes family birth, death, and marriage certificates, as well as two passports for Allyn and Ethel Cox; membership cards and awards and certificates including a National Academy of Design certificate of merit, 1963; personal financial records including notes on the dispostion of Cox's possesions, circa 1975-1981, and notes and lists related to sales of furnishings from the Cox family home in Essex, Massachusetts. Also found is an untranscribed 1974 sound recording of an interview of Allyn Cox by Tony Janak of NBC TV.
  - Addresses, circa 1940s-circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Awards and Certificates, 1916-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Oversized material housed in Box 12 Folder 1
  - Biographical Notes and Resumes, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Birth, Death and Marriage Records, and Miscellany, 1903-1960s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Calling Cards from European Trip, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Interview with Cox by Tony Janak of NBC TV, 1974 February 18; 1 sound tape reels Typed label on original box: "Allyn Cox House of Representatives/Muralist NBCTV 12/18/74 From: Tony Janak Speed 3/3/4" (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Membership Cards, 1950s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Passports, 1936, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Personal Financial Records, 1940-1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Sale of Essex Home Furnishings, Lists and Notes, circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Trip to Greece, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Will Documentation for Ethel Cox, 1920s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Oversized Awards and Certificates from Box 1, Folder 4 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1878-1982; Series 2; 6.74 Linear feet Boxes 1-7, 12, OV 13
  Arrangement note
  Correspondence is arranged as two subseries.
  2.1: Family Correspondence, 1878-1982
  2.2: General Correspondence, 1916-1982
  Personal, family, and professional correspondence document Cox's relationships with family members, friends, and colleagues, as well as his many private and public commissions, and his roles in professional organizations and clubs.
  - Family Correspondence, 1878-1982; 2.1
    Family correspondence includes 5 folders of letters written by Cox to family members, primarily his mother, Louise Cox, from circa 1916-1922 and 5 folders of Louise Cox's letters, primarily to Allyn Cox, from 1916 to the 1940s.
    Cox's relationships with his siblings is documented in 6 folders of correspondence with his sister, Caroline Cox Lansing, and 3 folders of correspondence with his brother, Leonard Cox, and Leonard's wife, Sylvia.
    There are two letters from Kenyon Cox to his half brother William Cochrane, in addition to a biographical sketch of Kenyon Cox, probably written by William, and a letter to Kenyon Cox from Bertha Beckwith. Ethel Cox's correspondence, 1915-1937, consists primarily of letters to her mother and documents her first trip abroad in 1920. Two additional folders of letters from circa 1915-circa 1940s and one from 1941-1971 include correspondence with others, including Allyn Cox, whom she married in 1927.
    Also of note are 3 folders of correspondence and records relating to the disposition of Kenyon Cox's Estate undertaken by Allyn Cox and his siblings in the late 1950s-1960s. The correspondence documents gifts of Kenyon Cox's paintings, drawings, and personal archives to various institutions including Bowdowin College, Columbia University, Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art, the Library of Congress, and the Smithsonian Institution. Additional correspondence related to this disposition, as well as correspondence with members of Cox's extended family, may be found in 2.2: General Correspondence.
    - Cox, Allyn to Family, circa 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
    - Cox, Allyn to Family, 1918-1922 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
    - Cox, Ethel, circa 1915-circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
    - Cox, Ethel, 1915-1971 (Box 1, Folder 22-34)
    - Cox, Jacob and Phyllis, 1940s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Cox, Kenyon, 1878; 1913-1917 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Cox, Kenyon, Disposition of Kenyon Cox Estate, 1958-1968 (Box 1, Folder 37-39)
    - Cox, Leonard and Sylvia, 1940s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 40-42)
    - Cox, Louise, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Cox, Louise to Allyn Cox, 1916-1940s (Box 1, Folder 44-47)
    - Lansing, Caroline Cox, 1929-circa 1982 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
    - Lansing, Cornelius, 1950s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, 1916-1982; 2.2
    Correspondence is arranged alphabetically, typically in named files for those correspondents represented with 5 or more items, and general letter files for all others.
    General correspondence documents Cox's career and professional relationships with artists and architects, art institutions and organizations, federal, state and local government agencies and members of congress; private clients including banks and residences; and private social clubs in which Cox was active.
    Cox's work at the United States Capitol is well represented here through correspondence, resumes, legal documents including contracts, condition reports, congressional reports and resolutions, and photographic material. Substantial correspondence between Cox and Representative Frank Schwengel document their earliest discussions when Cox first indicated his interest in the Capitol commission, and their ongoing professional relationship as the work continued. Also found is correspondence with artists Arthur Conrad, Adrian Lamb and Deane Keller who worked under Cox in his capacity as supervising artist on the portraits for the Senate Reception Room; and correspondence with the United States Capitol Historical Society, the office of the Architect of the Capitol, the Smithsonian Institution, and various historical societies and organizations with whom Cox consulted during the research phases of the Capitol projects. Correspondence with Cox's assistant, Cliff Young, is generally filed separately.
    14 folders of records including correspondence, memoranda, and contracts, document Cox's work for the George Washington Masonic National Memorial.
    American Battle Monuments Commission records include correspondence and contracts with architects Francis Keally and John Harbeson, and mosaic fabricator Fabrizio Cassio. Also found is correspondence with: architects John Barrington Bayley, Charles Downing Lay, Philip Trammell Shutze, with whom Cox collaborated on a variety of private residences including the Calhoun House in Atlanta, Georgia, and Roscoe DeWitt, who worked with Cox on a commission for St. Paul's Hospital in Dallas, Texas; artists Stuart Frost, Edward Laning; historian Bernard Berenson; interior decorator Emma Romeyn; journalist Joseph C. Harsch; models, including Jay Martin; and writer Katharine Hayden Salter who wrote many letters to Cox on the subject of Kenyon Cox.
    Dumbarton Oaks records include correspondence with Mildred Bliss, Venetian Art Mosaics Inc Studio, and others involved in the project to replace Cox's deteriorating exterior loggia mural of Diana and Actaeon with a glass mosaic design of the painting. Cox's work with Venetian Art Mosaics Inc. also extended to other projects, such as the mosaic panels for the General Grant National Memorial (formerly Grant's Tomb), in New York City.
    Art Students League correspondence docments Cox's role as instructor at the League, 1940-1941. Art Commission of the City of New York records document Cox's service on the Art Commission.
    Correspondence with Nathaniel Pulsifer, and with Essex County Greenbelt Assocation, documents matters related to the Cox Reservation, a property purchased by Allyn Cox in 1940 as a summer home with a barn which he used as his studio, and which he donated to the Essex County Greenbelt in 1974.
    Cox's membership in private social organizations, including nomination and acceptance of new members, can be found in the the Century Association, Cosmopolitan Club, and Cosmos Club folders.
    - Aitken, Webster, 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Alderson-Broadus College (re: Cox's Honorary Degree), 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Aldrich, Chester, circa 1919 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Allen Tucker Memorial, 1960-1978 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Alsop House, Wesleylan University, 1948-1951 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
    - American Academy in Rome, 1918-1970s (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - American Artists Professional League, 1940s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - American Association of Museums, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - American Battle Monuments Commission, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 17-24)
    - American Battle Monuments Commission, 1950s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 25)
      Oversized material housed in OV 13
    - American Museum of Natural History, 1950-1955 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Archer, N., circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Architectural League of New York, 1940s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Archives of American Art, 1967-1977 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Art Bulletin, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Art Commission of the City of New York, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 31-32)
    - Art Commission of the City of New York, 1950s-1976 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Art Commission of the City of New York, Calendars, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Art Commission of the City of New York, Meeting Minutes, 1955-1958 (Box 2, Folder 35-37)
    - Art Students League of New York, 1940-1967 (Box 2, Folder 38-39)
    - Artists for Victory, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - A, General, 1919-1981 (Box 2, Folder 41-42)
    - Bacon, Herbert M., circa 1940s-circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Bancroft, John T., 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Bayley, John Barrington, circa 1960s-circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Bechtel, Edwin De T., 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Beekman, Bob, 1950s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Bentzen, Betty and Lyle, circa 1961-circa 1981 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Berenson, Bernard and Mary, 1917-1950s (Box 2, Folder 49-50)
    - Binger, Walter D., circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Bishop, Warner, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 52-53)
    - Blakeman, Ray, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Board of Education, City of New York, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 55-56)
    - Bouhan, William L., 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Bower, Jerry, 1964-1967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Brooklyn Museum, 1958-1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Brown, Ellen Morrill, circa 1974-1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Brown, Harris, Stevens, Inc., 1950-1954 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Brown, John Nicholas, Roelker Memorial, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Burns, Charlene and Gene, circa 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Butler Institute of American Art, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - B, General, 1917-1982 (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
      includes letter from Barbara Bush
    - Castle Hill Foundation, 1955-1961 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Century Association, circa 1940-1981 (Box 3, Folder 13-15)
    - Citizens Committee for the Army and Navy, Inc., 1941-1945 (Box 3, Folder 16-18)
    - Clarke, Gilmore D., circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Cleveland Trust Company, 1941-1973 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Columbia University, 1972-1977 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Cortini, Publio, circa 1960s-circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Cosmopolitan Club, 1933-1976 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Cosmos Club, 1970s-1982 (Box 3, Folder 24-25)
    - Cosmos Club, re: Fred Schwengel, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - County of New York, 1940s-1950s (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Cox, Peter, 1950s-1981 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Cram & Ferguson, Architects, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - C, General, 1934-1981 (Box 3, Folder 30-32)
    - Dana, Richard and Nathalie, circa 1927-1981 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - De Koven, WFUV, 1960s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - de Manduit, Priscilla, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Detroit Institute of Arts, 1980-1982 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Dixon Gallery and Gardens, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Dodge, Grover N. and Lydia, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Dumbarton Oaks, 1944-1970s (Box 3, Folder 39-41)
    - D, General, 1940s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Edward W. Minte Co. Inc, 1948-1958 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Emma Romeyn Inc., 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      OV material housed in OV 13
    - Ernest Peixotte Memorial Committee, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Essex County Greenbelt Association, 1970s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - E, General, 1916-1980s (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Farquhar, Robert D., circa 1950s (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Federated Garden Clubs of New York State, Inc., 1945-1950 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Fine Arts Federation of New York, 1940s-1980 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Frost, Stuart, 1953-1976 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - F, General, circa 1940s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Garland Publishing, Inc., 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - General Grant National Memorial, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 54-55)
    - George C. Marshall Research Foundation, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - George Washington Masonic National Memorial, 1947-1951 (Box 3, Folder 57-59)
    - George Washington Masonic National Memorial, 1952-1974 (Box 4, Folder 1-11)
      Oversized material housed in Box 12, Folder 2
    - George Washington Masonic National Memorial Association, Knights Templar Project, 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 12-14)
    - Grand Jury Association, New York, circa 1947 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Grand Lodge of North Carolina, 1957-1959 (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
    - Greener, George C, Masonic Throne, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 18)